

# **Ahmad Saqib**

**Email:** ahmadsaqib1@gmail.com | **Mob**: 07456860620 **Address**: 66 Belchers Lane, Birmingham, B8 3EU (relocatable)

Dedicated Science educator with 7+ years' experience across various age groups. I am passionate about science in general. Able to teach Chemistry and Biology at A-levels and all three sciences and Maths at GCSEs. Committed to promote science in school environment and inspire young students to participate in related fields.

# **Experience**

Forest Gate Community School – London, UK | Comprehensive school | Sept 2022 – Present | https://www.forestgatecst.org/ | Teacher | Subjects: Physics, Chemistry and Biology

- Teaching lessons at an appropriate level to include all pupils, aiding their understanding
- Collaborating with Lead, Assistant Teachers and Administrators to ensure students' safety
- Promoting in-class engagement and good behaviour by implementing school's policy
- Planning & Leading lessons using presentations, textbooks and other learning materials

**Wood Green School** – Witney, UK | Comprehensive PGCE placement school | April 2022 – July 2022 | https://wgswitney.org.uk/ | Science Teacher | Subjects: Physics, Chemistry and Biology

- Contributing to the effective and efficient running of science lessons for KS3, KS4 and KS5.
- Planning and teaching remedial sessions for struggling students
- Marking work according to departmental marking policies.
- Encouraging pupils to respond to the feedback.

**Chenderit School** – Middleton Cheney, UK | Comprehensive PGCE placement school | Sept 2022 – March 2022 | www.chenderit.northants.sch.uk | Science Teacher | Subjects: Science (KS3, KS4 & KS5)

- Organizing supplies and resources for lectures and presentations.
- Raising standards of achievement and maximising student attainment.
- Managing and organizing work for non-teaching staff.

Science and Mathematics Private Tutor - Birmingham, UK | Sept 2015 – Present | www.firsttutors.com/uk/tutor/ahmad.biology.chemistry.maths.physics.english.entrance-exams/ | Private Tutor | Subjects: Sciences - Physics, Chemistry and Biology |

- Educating students from KS1 to A-Levels (pre-university).
- Supporting young students with academic and career goals and manage their progress.
  - 90%+ success rate with students. All students have achieved their target grades.
- Creating personalized schemes of work, lesson plans and coaching to maximize results.
  - 90%+ success rate for helping student applications to secure a university place.
- Working closely with parents in order to design engaging session in order to help students achieve their target grades.
- Teaching via remote learning during lockdowns.

**Vital Educators Ltd** – Birmingham, UK | www.vitaleducators.com | Jan 2020 – Aug 2021 | *Managing Director* | Geography: National |

- Online student-teacher matching platform
- Nationwide Podcast on careers advise in STEM fields
- Free resources for Science GCSEs and A-levels

#### Academic Enrichment Centre – Birmingham, UK | Sept 2017 - Dec 2019 |

https://www.aectuition.co.uk/ | Science Teacher | Subjects: Physics, Chemistry and Biology

- Preparing reports on matters associated with the role, as required by the Centre.
- Giving clear feedback to parents on a pupil's progress on parents' evenings.
- Allocating and then grading homework, assignments, and tests.

## **Key Skills**

#### **Team Working and Leadership**

- Worked with the Placement School Science team to develop and deliver current science curriculum
- Led a group of five students on a research project on development of a novel treatment for breast cancer at University of Birmingham.
- Providing inspirational leadership as University Ambassador for Department of Education at University of Oxford to help prospective students discover more about the opportunities available in higher education.

#### **Communication**

- Confident communicator with people at all levels, in person, on the phone and in writing.
- Able to converse in English, Hindi, Punjabi & Urdu, currently learning basic Spanish.
- Able to constructively debate to tackle various current political, ethical and healthcare matters.
- Podcast host/ interviewer of scientists and other professionals in the UK

## Conflict resolution.

- Undertook additional online training in conflict resolution
- Published a research article at university on managing disruptive behaviour in class
- Applied researched methods and training to manage conflict in class

#### **Professionalism**

- Ability to work on own initiative, prioritising and managing time effectively.
- Committed to the protection and safety of pupils.
- Highly adaptable and flexible with lesson plans.
- Using a various methods and approaches to match curricular objectives and student needs.
- Strong organisational and reporting skills.
- Possesses a valid Disclosure and Barring Service Certificate.
- Researching current affairs areas to be included in science topics

## Other Skills & Interests

- Full UK driving license, School Information Management System (SIMS), Microsoft Office
- Mixed Martial Arts, Weight Lifting, Current Affairs, Travelling, Podcasts, Health & Fitness

# **Awards and Honours**

- Awarded highest achiever of the year in Secondary School
- Voted Best Student of the year in Secondary School
- University Ambassador for Education department at University of Oxford
- Given Allen Murray Scholarship and Chamberlain Award at University of Birmingham
- Given Teaching Scholarship by Royal Society of Chemistry at University of Oxford

#### **Education**

University of Oxford - Oxford, UK | Sept 2021 – July 2022 |

Postgraduate Certificate of Education (PGCE) in Science, Specialism in Chemistry, Pass

University of Birmingham - Birmingham, UK | 2012 - 2016 |

MSci Biochemistry, Second-class honours

King Edwards VI Grammar School - Birmingham, UK | 2009 - 2012 |

A levels: Mathematics (A), Chemistry (B), Biology (B), Urdu (A), Physics (B), G. Studies (B)

Heartlands High School - Birmingham, UK | 2008 - 2009 |

GCSEs, 8 A\*s, 3As including Mathematics and Physics, Chemistry and Biology

# References

- Lead Teacher of Science: Chadni Patel. Email: chadni.patel@forestgatecst.org
- Academic Tutor: Ann Childs. Email: ann.childs@education.ox.ac.uk